Guide to the Relyea Family Papers 1839-1924 (bulk 1860-1900) MS 518
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Relyea Family Papers
1839-1924
MS 518
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.3 Linear feet (1 box)
The papers cover over three generations of the Relyea family, but particularly concern Peter Relyea. The collection includes letters, legal documents, accounts, and also contains documents relevant to the Rosevelt family.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Biographical Note
The bulk of the papers revolve around Peter Relyea (1817-1896), a prosperous New York undertaker. He served in the New York State Militia during the 1830s and 1840s rising to the rank of lieutenant. Relyea also achieved prominence in his secondary field, having crafted the hearse that carried President Lincoln's body through New York City in 1865.
Relyea relocated to Williamsburg, Brooklyn in 1869, and was appointed an Official Undertaker of that city in 1881. Peter Relyea married Elizabeth Ryers in 1838. After her death in 1866, he married C.A. Decker. A long-time Freemason, Peter Relyea was buried in Greenwood Cemetery in Brooklyn with Masonic honors.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes various letters from Peter Relyea to his daughter Millie, letters to Willie Relyea from his cousin Henry, invitations addressed to Relyea family members to attend surprise parties, and letters addressed to Peter Relyea from business associates.
The collection also includes the military records of Peter Relyea, mortgages, real estate deeds, bonds, deeds to cemetery plots, receipts (including undertaker services rendered by Peter Relyea), and other various papers, such as a license granted to Peter Relyea to act as an Official Undertaker of the city of Brooklyn.
The collection also contains genealogy papers of the Rosevelt family (to which the Relyea family was related) and business papers of Rosevelt and Sullivan, the contracting partnership of Warren Rosevelt and John M. Sullivan. These concern the construction of a pile dock on Governors Island.
The Relyea Papers do not include any information regarding Peter Relyea's construction of Abraham Lincoln's hearse.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into folders by type of material. Items within the collection are arranged chronologically.
Relyea family; Relyea, Peter, --d. 1896 -Estate; Rosevelt family; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) - Buildings, structures, etc.; Buddington, Lucy Avery; Commissions; Correspondence; Deeds; Ephemera; Freemasons. -Americus Lodge (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Funeral rites and ceremonies - New York (State) - New York; Governors Island (New York County, N.Y.); Invitations; Invoices; Legal documents; Mortgages; New York (State) -Militia; Programs; Real property - New York (State) - New York; Relyea, Peter, d. 1896; Rosevelt & Sullivan; T. Rosevelt & Griffiths; Undertakers and undertaking - New York (State) - New York; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.) - Buildings, structures, etc. - Design and construction.
  - Agreements, Grave Deeds, Wills, 1845-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates (Confirmation and License), 1881-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters (Personal, Business, Invitations), 1867-1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Masonic Pamphlets Concerning Peter Relyea, 1864-1896 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Military Records of Peter Relyea, 1839-1849 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mortgages, Deeds, Bonds, 1868-1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Receipts/Billings, 1843-1894 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Relyea Family Genealogy, [1851-1938] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rosevelt Family Genealogy, [1869-1898] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rosevelt Papers (Contract Between W. Rosevelt & J. Westbrook), 1894 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rosevelt Papers (Envelopes, Construction Contracts, Letters), 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 11)